Ames Williams Collection, 1838-1976 [bulk 1960-1968]
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Ames Williams Collection, 1838-1976 [bulk 1960-1968]
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
63
3 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Ames Williams. The original donation took place in 1979. The scrapbook was added later.
Biographical/Historical Information
Ames Williams, a lawyer and authority on early Virginia railroads, wrote a photographic history of the Washington and Old Dominion Railroad in 1969. The Alexandria/Loudoun & Hampshire Railroad was established in 1853 to compete with the existing Baltimore & Ohio Railroad that had a monopoly on the Washington DC area. During the Civil War the railroad was controlled by both armies, and after the war it was left heavily damaged. Around 1870 the name was changed to the Washington & Ohio Railroad, and plans were made to expand up to the Ohio River, but money ran out, and they were forced to stop at Bluemont. In 1912 McLean and Elkins bought the railroad and renamed it the Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. After the railroad was purchased by the Chesapeake & Ohio Railroad in 1955, it began to decline. Following the purchase of the Rosslyn spur, the railroad continued to deteriorate until its closing in 1968.
Scope and Content
The collection relates to the Washington & Old Dominion Railroad.
Box 63 is organized into nine series. Legal documents comprise approximately half of the material. These legal documents concern the Interstate Commerce Commission's hearings dealing with the railroad's abandonment of its Virginia line. Of interest in the printed material series are ticket stubs and schedules from railroads.
Box 63A contains a series of 24 maps of 1916 Washington & Old Dominion Railway rights-of-way and tracks. Maps 1 and 4 are missing. These maps show where the line crossed Alexandria.
Box 63B contains a Washington & Old Dominion Railroad scrapbook, 1853-1968. The scrapbook contains copies of documents about the early Alexandria/Loudoun & Hampshire Railroad, including schedules and inventory. After about 1870 there are annual reports on the railroad until 1960, when proceedings began to close the railroad. There are many newspaper clippings describing arguments to keep the railroad open, and arguments to close the railroad. Since this was happening in the 1960's there are also some documents dealing with the centennial celebration of the Civil War.
Arrangement
Box 63: By type of document.
Box 63A: By map number.
Box 63B: By subject and thereunder chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also the vertical file under "railroads." The rare book collection includes annual reports of the railroads for 1859-1861 in the Biennial Report of Public Works to the General Assembly of Virginia, 351.8 Vir
Separated Material
32 prints, 1 negative, 77 slides transferred to Ames Williams photograph collection.
Index Terms
Railroads--Virginia--History; Washington & Old Dominion Railroad; Williams, Ames W. (Ames William)
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 63:1)
- Correspondence, 1963-1976 (Box-folder 63:2)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Exhibits Submitted on Behalf of Rail Travel Assoc. 1965 (Box-folder 63:3)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Report and Corrections. 1966 (Box-folder 63:4)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Exceptions Filed on Behalf of the Northern Virginia Transport. Comm. 1965 (Box-folder 63:5)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Exceptions Filed on Behalf of the Northern Virginia Transport. Comm. 1966 (Box-folder 63:6)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Exceptions Filed on Behalf of the Northern Virginia Transport. Comm. 1966 (Box-folder 63:7)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Exceptions to the Examiners Report. 1966 (Box-folder 63:8)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Orders. 1966-1968 (Box-folder 63:9)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Report of the Commission. 1968 (Box-folder 63:10)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Users Assoc. v. U.S.A. 1968 (Box-folder 63:11)
- Legal Documents - Washington & Old Dominion Abandonment. Miscellaneous. 1966 (Box-folder 63:12)
- Legal - Miscellaneous. 1838-1972 (Box-folder 63:13)
- Printed Material - Railroad Schedules. 1874-1947 (Box-folder 63:14)
- Printed Material - Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1907-? (Box-folder 63:15)
- Printed Material - Clippings (includes electric railroads). 1954-1976 (Box-folder 63:16)
- Printed Material - Clippings. 1978-1985 (Box-folder 63:17)
- Printed Material - Miscellaneous. Includes Luna Park, transportation in Alexandria, Little Sully, Pioneer America Society, Echoes of History. 1908-1958 (Box-folder 63:18)
- Maps (Box-folder 63:19)
- Research Notes (Box-folder 63:20)
- Research Notes (Box-folder 63:21)
- Drafts (Box-folder 63:22)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 63:23)
- Artifacts (Box-folder 63:24)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railway right-of-way and track maps. (Box 63A)
- Early Years / Civil War - Alexandria / Loudoun & Hampshire Railroad. 1853-1868 (Box-folder 63B:1)
- Biographical: Founders & Railroad. (Box-folder 63B:2)
- Use of by Armies in Civil War. 1861 (Box-folder 63B:3)
- H.R. Report. 1857-1887 (Box-folder 63B:4)
- Washington & Ohio Railroad Schedule. 1883-1907 (Box-folder 63B:5)
- Washington & Ohio Railroad, Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1871-1901 (Box-folder 63B:6)
- Notes. 1900-1961 (Box-folder 63B:7)
- Accidents, Employment. 1920-1923 (Box-folder 63B:8)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railroad Schedule. 1919 (Box-folder 63B:9)
- Schedule, Inventory. 1911-1932 (Box-folder 63B:10)
- Interstate Commerce Commission. 1925 (Box-folder 63B:11)
- Annual Report. 1889-1894 (Box-folder 63B:12)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railroad Annual Report. 1912-1921 (Box-folder 63B:13)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railroad Annual Report. 1922-1931 (Box-folder 63B:14)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railroad Annual Report. 1932-1941 (Box-folder 63B:15)
- Washington & Old Dominion Railroad Annual Report. 1942-1960 (Box-folder 63B:16)
- Correspondence. 1960 (Box-folder 63B:17)
- Washington & Old Dominion Rosslyn Terminal - Maps. 1916-1946 (Box-folder 63B:18)
- 50 Years Ago/100 Years Ago. 1960-1968 (Box-folder 63B:19)
- Civil War Centennial. (Box-folder 63B:20)
- Closing Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1960-1962 (Box-folder 63B:21)
- Closing Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1964-1965 (Box-folder 63B:22)
- Railroad Accident. 1966 (Box-folder 63B:23)
- Closing Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1966-1967 (Box-folder 63B:24)
- Closing Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. 1968 (Box-folder 63B:25)
- Closing Washington & Old Dominion Railroad. Undated (Box-folder 63B:26)